Guide to the National University records, 1875-1988 RG0123
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National University records
1875-1988
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National University (Washington, D.C.)
RG0123
44.5 Linear Feet
Collection of programs, yearbooks, correspondence, student records and grades, agreements, minutes, Senate and House bills, Congressional Records, and published works. The materials cover the dates 1872-1988.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by the university in 1954 when National University merged with GW, with subsequent accretions by the office of the President before its transfer to University Archives in 1987.
Historical or Biographical Note
National University was incorporated by an Act of Congress in June 1869. Dr. William B. Wedgewood was the school's founder. Five presidents of the United States, Grant, Garfield, Hayes, Arthur and Cleveland have acted as Chancellor ex-efficio of the National University as an indication of the caliber of the men who directed the affairs in its formative years.
Although instruction was first given in several professional fields, including a Department of Medicine, the tendency as the years passed was toward the law. Law constituted the predominant branch of the University, but it should not be overlooked that National's School of Economics and Government conferred the degrees of AB, BS, BCS, and MCS.
Because of rapid growth and changing conditions it was found necessary to reorganize the University in 1896. A new charter was granted by a special Act of Congress, (129 Stat. L. 194), conferring the power to grant university degrees. The new incorporators were all men holding high and honored positions in the Federal Judicial service.
At the death of President Cleveland the Board of Regents abolished the office of Chancellor ex-efficio and elected Arthur McArthur (Grandfather of Douglas McArthur), then a justice on the District of Columbia Supreme Court bench as the first Chancellor. Other Chancellors of National University included: Samuel F. Miller, Associate Justice of the United States Supreme Court, Charles S. Hatfield, Justice of the United States Count of Customs and Patent Appeals and Leslie C. Garnett, a former Assistant Attorney General of the United States.
In 1954 the National University merged with The George Washington University forming what became the National Law Center at The George Washington University.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains programs, yearbooks (The Docket), correspondence, student records and grades, agreements, minutes, Senate and House bills, Congressional Records, and published works. The materials cover the dates 1872-1988. With the bulk of the records falling within the date range 1900-42.
Collection Organization
Organized in three series: Two of Records, and Yearbooks.
Collection note
Many of the yearbooks, The Docket, were donated by Gunther L. Munter, who received his law degree from National University.
Yearbooks; Commencement ceremonies -- Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Law; Students; Courses and lectures; George Washington University; National University (Washington, D.C.). Law School
- Records, 1872-1988; RG0123 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains programs, yearbook, correspondence, records, agreements, minutes, House bills, Congressional records, Senate bills, published works. They range in date from 1872 to 1988. The materials concern National University Law School; commencement; convocations; "Stars Decisis" yearbook; National University Medical and Dental Departments; registered students; merger with George Washington University; National University's Board of Trustees; and the works of "Prospectus of a national institution, to be established in the United States", "Memorial in Regard to a National University", and "Proposed: the University of the United States".
  - National University--Law School, 06/1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - National University Law School Convocations/Commencements, 1884-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National University Yearbook Stare Decisis, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National University--Medical & Dental Dept.--Commencement Exercises, 05/17/1892-06/06/1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National University--Medical & Dental Department--Dean's Correspondence, 05/26/1896-03/28/1898 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National University--Medical & Dental Dept.--Students Registered & Graduated, 1884-1903, 09/13/1884-02/27/1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National University--Merger With GW, 1954, 07/04/1954-11/10/1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A National University Movement--History of the Idea (1781-1962), 12/1891-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A National University Movement --Reports to implement the idea 1967-72, 02/02/1967-01/13/1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A National University Movement --Supporting Documents, 05/04/1772-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A National University Movement --Supporting Documents The University of the United States by Edgar Bruce Wesley, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Group photograph portrait of the National University Law School class of 1889 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Portrait photograph of Charles F. Carusi (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Act incorporating National University, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees correspondence, 1954-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of the meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1954-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3-13)
- Yearbooks, 1922-1942; RG0123 Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains the yearbook, Dockets. These items cover the dates 1922-42.
  - Docket, 1922 (Volume 1)
  - Docket, 1925 (Volume 2)
  - Docket, 1926 (Volume 3)
  - Docket, 1927 (Volume 4)
  - Docket, 1928 (Volume 5)
    2 copies
  - Docket, 1929 (Volume 6)
  - Docket, 1930 (Volume 7)
  - Docket, 1931 (Volume 8)
  - Docket, 1932 (Volume 9)
  - Docket, 1933 (Volume 10)
  - Docket, 1934 (Volume 11)
  - Docket, 1934 (Volume 12)
  - Docket, 1935 (Volume 13)
  - Docket, 1936 (Volume 14)
  - Docket, 1937 (Volume 15)
  - Docket, 1938 (Volume 16)
  - Docket, 1939 (Volume 17)
  - Docket, 1940 (Volume 18)
  - Docket, 1941 (Volume 19)
  - Docket, 1942 (Volume 20)
- Records, 1875-1953; RG0123 Series 3; 42.5 Linear feet. Records in the first few boxes of Series 3 are leather-bound. The bindings are suffering from serious red-rot, and should be handled with care. (Box 28, Box 5, Box 29, Box 10, Box 11, Box 6, Box 8, Box 7)
  This series contains annual reports, bulletins and class descriptions, financial statements, student transcripts and grades for the National University Law School. This material dates from 1875-1953. National University merged with The George Washington University in 1954.
  - National University, 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National University, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National University, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National University, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National University, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National University, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National University, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National University, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National University, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National University, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National University, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National University, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National University, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1929-1930 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - National University, 1933-1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - National University, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1926-1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1928-1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1928-1929 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1929-1930 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1931-1932 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1931-1932 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1929-1930 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1930-1931 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1930-1931 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1932-1933 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1932-1933 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1935-1936 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1935-1936 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1935-1936 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - National University ,Vol. 4, 1935-1936 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1936-1937 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1936-1937 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1935-1936 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1936-1937 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1938-1939 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - National University, 1939-1940 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - National University, 1940-1941 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - National University, 1942-1943 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1936-1937 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 4, 1936-1937 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1937-1938 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1937-1938 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 4, 1937-1938 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1938-1939 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1938-1939 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1938-1939 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 4, 1938-1939 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1939-1940 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1939-1940 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 4, 1939-1940 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1939-1940 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1930-1931 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - National University, Vol. 3, 1937-1938 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - National University, Vol. 1, 1940-1941 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - National University, Vol. 2, 1940-1941 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1942-1943 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - National University, 1941-1942 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1943-1944 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1944-1945 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1932-1933 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - National University, 1944-1945 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - National University, 1945-1946 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - National University, 1946-1947 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - National University, 1947-1948 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - National University, 1948-1949 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - National University, 1949-1950 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Schedules to the Financial Statements, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report-Financial Statement and Schedules, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Schedules to the Financial Statement, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Annual report-Financial Report, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Five copies
  - Schedules to the Financial Statement for the Year Ended June 30, 1976, 06/30/1976 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Schedules to the Financial Statement for the Year Ended June 30, 1978, 06/30/1978 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report Including Financial Statement for the year Ended June 30, 1978, 06/30/1978 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - A Self-Study Report to the Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Commission on Higher Education, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
    The Report of the Evaluation Team from the Commission on Higher Education of the Middle states Association and the University response to that report; Five copies
  - Volume LXXVIII, No. 4, 07/1980 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - College of General Studies, 1979-1980 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Proposed National University certificate and National College of Pharmacy constitution, 1878-1907 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Materials include the constitution of the National College of Pharmacy dated 1878 and proposed certificate issued to graduates of National University dated 1907. This material dates from 1878-1907. National University merged with The George Washington University in 1954. Formerly ACC#557.